Finding Aid for Conant Family papers, 1833-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Conant Family papers 1833-2001
Conant family.
2008180 Aa 2; Ac; UAx
The Conant Family papers trace several generations of the Conant family in Van Buren Township, Wayne County and Salem Township, Washtenaw County. The collection contains Civil War correspondence, general family correspondence spanning a period of 130 years, warranty deeds regarding the Conant farmstead, genealogical research, photographs and negatives.
1 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in October 2008 by James Conant (donor no. 10119 ). Additional materials were received in 2014.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
In 1833, John Wesley Conant (1801-1877) left New York and settled his family in Van Buren Township, Wayne County, Michigan. The family purchased a farm on Denton Road and built a one and one-half story frame house that, as of 1989, was listed (after its relocation to Salem Township) on the State Register of Historic Places. John Wesley and wife Alice Van Pelt had three daughters and three sons. Their son John Stoughton Conant (1837-1897) became the next owner of the Conant farmstead in Van Buren Township.
On February 20, 1863, John Stoughton was drafted into Company H, Fourth Infantry and joined the regiment at Falmouth, Virginia on March 23, 1963. As a soldier during the Civil War, John Stoughton fought at the Battle of Gettysburg. He was later discharged at the expiration of term of service on November 11, 1863. Soon after, Conant married Cynthia Anne Lamkin (1845-1918) in Ypsilanti. The couple had three children, Mary (b. 1865), Ellen (b. 1868) and Eugene (b. 1880).
After the death of John Stoughton, Eugene Conant became the official owner of the family farm; however, his sisters Mary and Ellen continued to live in the family home. Along with sharing the home with his sisters, Eugene Conant and his wife Ella May Glass raised their two children Hebert Eugene (1905-1999) and Edith Belle (1907-1930) in the John Wesley Conant House.
Herbert Eugene married Olive Neubert in 1940. The couple moved into the Conant house with aunts Mary and Ellen. In 1941-1942, the Conant family received multiple offers to sell their farm to Henry Ford. The family declined to sell their land at the time; however, they were forced to move in 1942 when their land was purchased with the aim of building the Willow Run Bomber Plant. The family moved the John Wesley farmhouse and other outbuildings to its current location on the Bowers-Walker farm in Salem Township, Washtenaw County, Michigan.
The Conant Family papers cover the period between 1833 and 2001. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, warranty deeds, land documents, financial statements, newspaper clippings, genealogical research, photographs and negatives. The collection has the following series: Family, Land and Finances, Genealogy, and Visual Material.
Subjects:
Conant family.; Salem (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1861-1864). Company H.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Van Buren (Mich.: Township); Willow Run Airport (Mich.); Willow Run Bomber Plant.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Conant family.; Military uniforms.; Willow Run Airport (Mich.); Willow Run Bomber Plant.; Van Buren (Mich.: Township)
Genre Terms:
Daguerreotypes.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Family
  The Family series covers 130 years of the Conant family. The collection contains correspondence from John Stoughton Conant while he served with Company H, Fourth Infantry during the Civil War. Among John Conant's Civil War correspondence is a first hand account of the Battle of Gettysburg. The series also includes general family correspondence, government documents and certificates, and newspaper clippings.
  - Abraham Lincoln Funeral Sermon by Rev. Samuel Gorman 1865 (Box 1)
  - Army documents 1863-1897 (Box 1)
  - Civil War Correspondence 1863, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (5 July 1863 letter details the Battle of Gettysburg)
  - Correspondence 1847-1862 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1863-1898 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1910-1977 (Box 1)
  - Marriage Certificates 1864 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings undated (Box 1)
  - War Rations 1945 (Box 1)
- Land and Finances
  Land and Finances series documents the Conant family's financial activities, property development, and legal attempts to save their property during World War II from being used for the Willow Run Bomber Plant. The series contains abstracts of title, district maps, warranty deeds, land petitions, and financial documents.
  - Abstracts of Title 1942 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Farmers' Market Report 1946 (Box 1)
  - District Maps undated (Box 1)
  - Estate Documents 1833-1881 (Box 1)
  - Land Petitions 1942 (Box 1)
  - Legal correspondence about land titles 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Mortgage certificates 1873-1916 (Box 1)
  - Pension documents 1903-1981 (Box 1)
  - Warranty Deeds 1833, 1873-1942 (Box 1)
    (include land deed, 1833 in oversize folder)
- Genealogy
  Genealogy series contains genealogical research primarily focused on the John Wesley Conant family but also some research on other related Michigan families. The series includes personal narratives about family life, genealogical history, and a published booklet by Frederick Odell Conant about the Conant families of America, and a printed 1834 Emigrant's Directory describing routes through New York, Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, and Michigan.
  - Personal narratives/memories undated (Box 1)
  - Conant Genealogical Published Research by Frederick Odell Conant 1887 (Box 1)
  - Roger Conant Family Association 1913-1919 (Box 1)
  - John Wesley Conant House 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Other Families 1904-2001 (Box 1)
  - Genealogy Notebook undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Family Trees 1986 undated (Box 1)
  - Emigrant's Directory 1834 (Box 1)
  - Gettysburg Hat Story 1996 (Box 1)
- Visual Material
  Visual Material series includes formal family portraits, photographs of the Conant property and house, tintypes, and negatives.
  - Portraits circa 1860s-1890s, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Family Photographs circa 1860s-1910s (Box 1)
  - Family Photographs circa 1950s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Family Photographs circa 1990s (Box 1)
  - Buildings in Michigan including family house and churches 1971 undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph scans of early family photos undated (Box 1)
  - Negatives 1940s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Description of Negatives? undated (Box 1)
  - Denton School postcard undated (Box 1)
  - John Denton home, Denton Road circa 1887 (Box 1)
    tintype
  - John Conant and Family circa 1860s, daguerreotypes and tintypes (Folder UAx)
    (include image of young man in uniform identified as "Uncle Billy Lamkin Brother of Cynthia Conant)
    These images filed with UAx special care images.